[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
well welcome everyone to the stoa and
stoa is a digital campfire
where we cohere and dialogue at the
knife's edge
of this moment and today we are joined
here by tyson yonko porta
he wrote a book called sand talk how
indigenous thinking can save the world
and here at the stoa it seems a lot of
our conversations center around
saving the world solving the meta crisis
what is it that we can do where do we
have agency as a community
and tyson's book which i learned about
through jim rutt's podcast
it's been just really rich and
thought-provoking and
calling me into deeper participation
with
the world around me the earth the sand
the soil
the air and so we invited him near the
stowa and we're really lucky to have him
here and i know a lot of you have been
reading the book or listening to the
book which is uh incredible audio
performance
by the way i really appreciate when uh
author reads their own book
but especially when it's read like i'm
i could imagine myself sitting around a
campfire with you
so i really recommend the audiobook even
if you've
read the book and there's gonna be a lot
of good questions coming in i
imagine so i want to make as much space
and time for that
as we can and i think i'll
um well tyson i'll say welcome and
invite you to
say hello and if you have any opening um
comments or anything and
i'd love to invite that hey how he's all
going
um i i don't know if you're all in the
estates or you're from lots of places
around the world
you know but um yeah it's it's
always good to think about the uh first
people's
uh where you are and so um
yeah it's tricky on zoom because always
multiple places at once um but
yeah but i'm on the land of the
bunarong mob here in
melbourne
and arnie
as the person who
is the senior elder who gives me
permission to uh to be here and
you know do this podcast and do this
work here
so i'm pretty much coming under her law
um yeah and so she gives me a slap from
time to time if i go
the wrong way i say the wrong thing it's
funny because i say some terrible things
sometimes
she doesn't say anything but then like
uh somewhere in my book i refer to
to wattle a wattle spirit as male
and she flogged me for that like
she's like no that's female i'm gonna
yeah anyway um
she's got a big stick and she she flogs
me with it
yeah so uh yeah
just uh just get grounded in the idea of
the
first peoples there and the old people
who are still uh in custodial
relationship with your place and um
and the big sticks that they carry uh
especially the women because they'll
just they'll just flog you
yeah and that's it
thank you welcome it's not a standard
acknowledgement but
for all those of you that have questions
you can go ahead and type them in the
chat and
um i will be calling on you to i meet
yourself and ask your question
if you would like me to ask your
question for any reason then you can say
so and i'll read your question for you
uh tyson when you said permission i felt
uh this sort of like spark in me like a
recalling of a maybe
a feeling that i sometimes seek out
when i've in the way that i've been
learning about the world and seeking
uh wisdom and and new ideas and and
deeper ideas and rich wisdom traditions
i find uh sort of a sense in myself
wherever i am in the world to want to
uh i mean know more learn more about
the indigenous cultures and also have
a a more participatory experience
and i found in myself um this this
question that i've been asking myself
and uh and now those around me how i
might
how i might seek wisdom and in
a more participatory way with the
indigenous cultures on the land that i'm
at and and where i find um i went on a
hike the other day and i found this
trail called like red ochre falls or
something and i found these
pots of um of red oak like in the spring
coming from the ground and there's these
signs sort of illustrating how they
might have been used
by indigenous cultures and then there's
people standing around and taking photos
and i had this sense like what would it
be like to play in there and have that
experience but it felt to me
off limits and so my curiosity was like
what is the way in which i can
with wisdom and respectfully and learn
about this in a more participatory way
and so that's what my my question
circles around i'd love to hear
some of your thoughts around that
yeah it's it's tricky isn't it i mean
there's a lot of um
like i i i know in the states there's a
lot of similar
uh problems to hear that when um
so as indigenous people when we try to
go
and um and do our thing you know on the
land in places especially national parks
and things like that there's a lot of
hostility
and so we found that we we have to kind
of sneak in there when there's no one
around and then hope that the rangers
don't get to us
you know so like i don't know i just i
just imagine
in that scene that you're talking about
you know people just sort of waiting for
for all the tourists to leave or all the
visitors to leave so they could come in
and get
some oka you know um
yeah i just um
yeah there's a there's a
big mob um to the north a bit that that
i've done a lot of
sort of ceremony and things with um
and yeah there's
they um they got stopped in the middle
of a ceremony
and it was it was men's ceremony you
know
and there were like um uh female park
rangers coming in and
and berating them and putting out their
fire
and like you know wanted to give them
fines and all this sort of stuff because
they
they had their special fire going in
that place
and um it's like and the rangers were
going no you've destroyed that heritage
site
you know that ancient fireplace is um
australian heritage you know and
and you've wrecked it by lighting a fire
in the same place on the fireplace where
your ancestors have done ceremony
forever
you know you you've put a fire there and
that's wrecked the heritage status of
that because
now it's been used recently it's ruined
you know um yeah that was huge
um so i mean that was a terrible thing
you
there were a lot of men i don't know we
were all uh
really angry about that and i wasn't
there for that incident
thank god you know because i'm a bit of
a hothead
and they um i don't know so they they
all got together and decided and we
we called in fellas from all over so all
over the continent we call
and we're like you know we're trying to
get hundreds and hundreds of men all
together in one place
um you know to do that ceremony and then
you know to resist and fight if anyone
came in and tried to kick us off
from doing it um but i don't know
so um i don't know the government did
you know what they always do to quell
rebellions i mean there's one of two
things they'll do you either throw you
in jail or they'll give you money
and so they gave somebody some money and
i don't know they made it
into like they took like this uh big uh
uprising
you know restless natives was going to
happen
you know so what they did was they they
made it into like a festival
they funded all these stalls and tents
and and
you know all these things coming in and
um
yeah it ended up just being this big
event instead and that was the way they
controlled it
um yeah it's it's it's it's really
interesting this is kind of jujitsu
happening
you know between the traditional law of
your first peoples
and the the continuation um the
continuity of that law
there's kind of this jujitsu happening
between that and the settler state
um always and this kind of constant
erasure
uh that's going on and um you know
whether it's done nicely like that or
whether it's done you know um
by like you know shooting people or
locking them up or whatever
it's always an act of violence um you
know so it is
really tricky it's not like um you know
well i wonder what this ochre used to be
used for
you know i'll bet you there's people
still using that
but they have to come in when there's no
one no one around
and sort of steal their own ochre from
the state
um yeah that's a kind of dark way to
start this thing let's
try to move towards something a bit more
fun
yeah you can get me in a bad mood and
i'm just going to be all
no good well anybody that has questions
please do
drop them in the chat and i'll call on
you to ask
your question and joe
rivera you have a question and if you
would like to unmute yourself and ask it
i'd love to invite you to do so
for sure you guys can hear me yes yeah
okay perfect um to keep up the high
spirits and talks about violence
and death um i had a question tyson
about your book
um so it's sort of putting your book in
conversation
with the work of renee girard who i've
read recently
about violence um and a key insight of
his work if you've read it or if you're
familiar
is that there's an existential threat to
violence as we're experiencing it in the
west
if he's right then our sort of
repression of local violence will result
in a build-up and a release of violence
at a much larger level
um and like you know the 20th century
and the atrocities that happened then is
sort of the perfect example of
what it could look like um and you know
the next time that happens it'll be even
worse
according to his theory um but the
solution he proposes which
seems to be pretty popular in the sort
of game b crowd that
you know a lot of us sort of walk in um
is to make
sacred all-violence in order to sort of
break free of that memetic cycle that
puts the entire species at risk
in your book you take the opposite
perspective it seems um sort of calling
for
swift and memorable violence at a local
level
but also immediate forgiveness which
also sounds
like highly attractive and i was just
wondering more if you could sort of
expand upon the sort of punishment
system that
the first peoples use um and how that
works and
where you see that interacting with sort
of gerard's theory that we need to
basically abolish violence well it's not
really a punishment system punishment is
is sort of a small part of it um
but yeah it's your policing is not
something that's that's just conferred
into the hands of a few powerful people
it's something
like violence like everything like
governance
it's distributed uh throughout the
system and it keeps moving
in that kind of dynamic subordination
you know so depending on the context
and the knowledge that's needed uh but
also
particularly the place and which family
or which
person speaks for that place of where
you might be
you know that's where that authority is
um
now with the violence it is it is highly
ritualized
and highly rule governed and it looks
like chaos but it's not
you know it's it's it's highly
rule-governed
um so basically it minimizes the damage
uh the physical damage that's done and
then there's a lot of follow-up
protocols as well
so for example uh down here where i'm
staying now
there was a protocol in the old days of
you know anybody that you injured in a
battle or in a fight
which was highly controlled that you
would be responsible for their care
afterwards so you know it's really hard
to
like maim someone up really badly if you
know that you're going to be responsible
for their care
you're only going to want to hurt them
badly enough for
you know okay well i can look after this
this guy for two weeks i'm gonna give
him two weeks worth of damage
because that's all i'm prepared to do
you know um
you know there's other things i
mentioned in the book like um you know
with uh
knife fighting um the winner of the
night fight knife fight
has to be cut up exactly the same as the
loser
you know so the person with the most
cuts is the loser but then the winner
like they stand them side by side and
they look where the cuts are
and they cut them so that both of them
have exactly the same cuts
and yeah i've participated in that one
and it's
it's very hard it's very hard
thing to do to cut somebody else if
you're um
if you're going to get the same cut and
i think that's that's the point of it
you realize that you're just hurting
yourself you know
so there's a lot of things like that and
different places have different ideas
so then there's also the um there's the
other mob to the norther here who they
developed
a martial arts system based on the way
kangaroos fight
um you know because they don't get
really badly injured but it's
incredibly violent but there's rules you
know protocols and
and so there's this this big explosion
of violence and everybody walks away
from it unscathed but
they get it out of their system you know
um
yeah and i suppose you have to do that
look there's i don't know if you come
ever come across the work of
a a an anthropologist called napoleon
shanian
um he studied he did this um
seminal study of the yanamani indians in
the amazon
who he called the most violent people on
earth and so he videotaped
you know hundreds of hours of footage of
just big
brawls in the community people fighting
and i've watched quite a bit of that
and it's funny they seem to be wrestling
mostly and like screaming and writhing
around
there's not much physical damage being
done
um but then if you look into his work
you see that
i don't know um is anyone here come
across the continuum concept
uh that book so that's that was a very
exactly the same people but studied by a
woman who was looking at
childbirth and child wearing practices
she reports a very different experience
of those people
you know very peaceful very happy
people because of her approach to that
study
but this fella he he came in and he he
gave them gifts immediately
and like machetes and axes and things
like this
and those people hadn't seen steel
before and so they you know they started
fighting over those gifts and he filmed
them fighting
but it's funny you see them with the
machetes but they don't use the machetes
in the fire
you know they're mostly wrestling and
anyway
he decided so he got them to um
in exchange he got them to report to him
all of their genealogies
so who was related to whom and then
after
they reported that to him he fed it into
the computer
to do an analysis of their kinship
system to see who was related to whom
and then spent thousands of hours uh
watching the videotapes
and he noted a pattern whereby you know
people who were related to each other
would look after each other in the
fights
and people who were closely related
wouldn't fight each other
and they'd support each other against
other opponents
and uh his argument was that these
people were so primitive
that they couldn't possibly hold all
that genealogical
information in their heads only a
computer could do that
so therefore they were being driven by
something unconscious
even though they told him their
genealogies that's how he found out
about it he said they couldn't possibly
know it
it was so weird um
but people took his work seriously and
so out of that came the idea of that
that selfish gene idea
the idea that people are machines who
have no
real conscious choice about their
behavior but it's just
your genetics are driving you um
you know as an as as an individual agent
in the world
you know you're going to be selfish
because your genes are selfish and all
they want to do is replicate
so your behaviors will be driven by that
and that all of those behaviors can be
figured out with algorithms
on a computer and i mean you know what
that gave rise to next hey
you know all these the neoliberalism and
social fragmentation
um that idea of the human being as a
consumer that can be manipulated
um and that you know i mean the entire
uh system that's developed over the last
30 40 years
uh has been around that idea so that
that
the idea of liberalism uh the idea of
freedom and liberty that's been imposed
on the world
you know is this idea of individuals
going around fulfilling
whatever their wants and desires are and
that somehow in the aggregate that forms
the invisible hand of the marketplace
and that that will just the market will
solve everybody you don't need community
you don't need family you don't need
governance
it's you know it's the
marketplace that'll sort it out but then
also that within that
people can be manipulated you know
uh you know into behaving in certain
ways
um you know through their algorithms and
you know what that's turned into with uh
social media and and all of the rest all
these
mobile phone devices all that sort of
thing it goes right back to that old
asshole anthropologist buddy projecting
his
weird ideas onto indigenous people
and like i said if you read the
continuum concept a female
anthropologist would see a completely
different thing
when she goes in and she's looking for
child-rearing practices
she sees a very different culture there
with very different conclusions
um yeah sorry that was a really long
answer
but it's kind it's kind of important
because it it establishes this idea that
the
the primitive is something that you know
civilization
must project its own narratives back
onto
you know in order to support this idea
of progress
this idea of growth this idea of
development
so you know the myth of progress can
only exist with a mythological
um you know paleolithic past
of of brutality and simplicity and
stupidity
and the fittest survive you know so they
get all the desirable traits like you
know
um you know like
i i don't know stuff like you know rape
is normal and
and you know secretly every woman wants
to get raped i mean you must have seen
those studies
you know um you know and they just
project it like
they say they're being scientific but
they're projecting a narrative backwards
that they have no proof for that just
yeah that goes back to caveman times
when everybody was raped
it's just you know and they picture they
walk around in nature and it's just like
you know
that's all these plants and animals just
raping each other that's just the
natural
thing but as human beings we're rising
above that we've developed we have
progress
and you know so we have to control
ourselves and we have to control
everybody
otherwise it's just going to be endless
rape and murder um
it's just we all know that's not true
um but for some reason we're all going
along with the narrative
and that narrative is bullshit and we
know it
anyway that guy's dead now that
anthropologist
if he wasn't i'd be paying him a visit
yeah um
did somebody say something about carving
and then i just got to grab something
next one question keep talking that's
young
hello uh tyson wagner are you uh
you there with us i'm here do you hear
me now yep
great sorry about that maya will you ask
your question
hi tyson my name's maya i'm in warranty
country just
that river from you in warburton
i'll be damned not far from um
project 3488 i've mark told me the
rumors
yeah that's where we're getting married
i know congratulations now that i can
afford it
um i've lived here for
10 years in this um beautiful mountain
village
there's a mountains outside the window
there
um and i came here to
after walking the length of the yarra
river as a
the songline they are following
following some deep journeys to
try to come home here and do my best to
uh listen to country and learn that
place
and um yeah really put down the roots
and do the work
and it's been pretty amazing
but one thing i just loved your book
what i really appreciated was your
explanation of how a whole community
works to hold wisdom
and knowledge and you know as
a whitey in a village mainly of
um colonizers who all have
very very different narratives about
place and belonging
how to sort of work
as a community to develop collective
meaning so i've been running pilgrimages
to
to um visiting all the mountains in the
river and so forth so taking the kids
and every year climbing higher
and sort of growing into these places
and really
making commitment through coming into
relationship with country
um but the difference the difficulty
sorry i'll try and get the point the
difficulty between
my own deep personal experience of being
in country
that's very powerful compared to trying
to hold
a hold space for community connection
to to places when we don't have much
shared
ritual or meaning about um
country and the depth of
the depth of relationship with the more
than human world that is possible
so i know what you mean interested in
your thoughts about
how to develop collective connection in
such a fractured
kind of world yeah
well it comes out of the first one i
mean it's
it's easy enough to control your own
behaviors
you know or to influence yourself
you know despite what the studies of the
yanomani indians tell us
you can actually decide to walk along
the river
and it's not your selfish genes making
you do it you know
um but when you're doing that you're
interacting with a dynamic
complex self-organizing sentient system
that's filled with sentient uh human and
non-human entities
you know other than humans and you know
and there's something of a it's not a
surrender but it's an acceptance
you know when you start to you obviously
have reached that where you come into
that
that place and you become part of a
field that is
observing itself um
yeah so you're no longer standing
outside of the field observing it and
going oh this is an ecosystem and this
is connected to this and this is
connected to this and
i understand the secret system now
you're actually in it
and you're not trying to observe it
you're just part of a system that's
observing itself
and you're accepting those flows of
information hey tyson flows
you're getting the those flows of
information coming through and you're
not trying to accumulate it
and walk away with a hypothesis or a
story to share or anything like that
you're just letting it
come through you and then letting it go
and letting it change you
letting it transform you and you're
adapting to that place
and all kinds of entities of spirit and
um you know little parasites microscopic
things they're all coming into you
they're in that place
and they're changing you and making you
part of that place
and warburton is as good a place as any
to do it
it's probably the you know one of the
only
one of the few sort of living places
left in around this horrendous city
uh where we are here i mean it's
horrible this this city
you know built on a destroyed swamp is
it's really terrible um yeah but see
that's that
that's that sort of individual work but
i mean it starts out like that but
you're really coming into a collective
anyway
and so i'd say that's the answer to the
second part of your question
you know how to connect with others is
that you can't force it you know
if you think you've come away from your
individual work
on the land with an idea of how things
should be
or you think you have an answer or you
think you have a solution
or you think you have a set of tasks
that you're going to do that's going to
be helpful
or you've learned something and you
think oh everybody should know this
everybody should know this everybody
should think like this
if everybody thought like this the world
would be a better place i'm going to
make change
i'm going to be the change i want to see
in the world you're an idiot
you know because everything you've
learned
from you know that that um
that that flow state and that emergence
that you've experienced within yourself
and within that system you know from
being part of that system you've
destroyed it right there
you know and you have to interact with
the wider community
and everyone in the world in the same
way as you do when you work walking
country and
you're you're basically fostering the
conditions for emergence
and following that and allowing that to
transform you
that's all you can do if you have a
think you have a plan for changing the
world
or finding a solution to the problems of
the world
you're an idiot it's um it doesn't work
you can't design these things you know
you have to allow them and and coming
into a community
or allowing a community to coalesce
around a basin of attraction or whatever
that's um that's a good thing but the
the minute someone tries to like start
leading that
like or being a thought leader or like
some kind of intellectual on a pedestal
or some kind of boss for that it's just
ridiculous
man people invite me all the time to
become part of these
these new little networks or um or
fucking um
what they call them like are they you
know like a a
an activist group or a you know a
network that's going to make change in
the world or whatever
and if they and they start out with a
whole heap of really good people coming
together and
and just pinging off each other and and
it's really
generative and amazing and you start to
see transformations happen
you know and then all of a sudden you
get an email from
some self-appointed committee within it
who's decided to organize it all and
these are the dates and this is what
we're gonna do and
you know this is the treasurer and this
is the secretary it's finished
it's it's finished i've seen like five
of them like rise and fall this year
five of them i've been involved with
reluctantly as soon as you give it a
name
and um it's finished
yeah i wanted to ask you
how indigenous thinking can save the
world is your byline was that the
publisher then
yeah that's not my byline yeah i thought
so
you know the chapter uh forever ltd
for forever limited yeah that was my
title
was forever ltd and that was
um you know which is not good i mean it
takes too much too long to explain that
no one understands what that means
no one's gonna buy a book called forever
ltd but that was the point
it was like i don't want to name it and
and that that
title itself was sort of it was trying
to get across the idea that as soon as
you name something it's finished
it's corporatized it's branded and it's
stuffed so i was i was trying to
ironically do that
um and so i only had the goal of
connecting with a few hundred people
through the book who might read it
and you know just um because i can
manage a few hundred relationships um
but anyway it kind of went the other way
and it went how indigenous thinking
could save the world
you know at a time whenever there's a
crisis of meaning and
and and people are obsessed with sense
making and they're looking
anywhere and considering weird stuff
um so it's ended up um you know suddenly
there's
you know a hundred thousand
relationships that i just can't manage
at all um yeah
so i'm doing the podcast because that's
that's new campfire and
i can at least you know superficially
touch base with
people so i apologize to that for anyone
who's read the book and
there's a promise of a relationship
there and of an ongoing dialogue that
i assumed i'd be able to fulfill
and i just yeah i can't do it
oh really i'm personally really glad
that you get to be here with us
right now and if that book did find
me and find a lot of us here albert will
you ask
your question and then benjamin if you
want to tag in right after
and add anything because you had a
similar question then um go ahead
albert uh thank you so much for being
here tyson uh
your book was absolutely amazing um
and one of the parts of it that really
stood out for me that i'm really
intrigued by
was how you began your sense making
process your your
your cognitive process of picking out a
topic by crafting a tool
and then um going through this whole
process and like each
part of the tool will like represent
some part of your thinking so
if you'd be so gracious um could you
maybe demonstrate or
kind of like show that process that
would be amazing
yeah i saw that uh question pop up so i
was thinking about how to do that
uh so i grabbed a couple of things um
i don't know so you you find it in a lot
of the
um the basic visual images and
communications of knowledge
you know there's a circle and there's
and there's kind of a a square or a
diamond or a triangle kind of thing um
like you always see these things um
in a lot of the in a lot of the shapes
for the symbology you know um
and it's kind of how carving goes as
well
but so i mean you can see and this male
or female energy stuff in there
and you probably can't really see it
there it's not a very good image
but you so you can see that male kind of
orion
constellation you know that all around
the world is called the hunter you know
or the warrior you know um
and that's and that's that kind of you
know square or diamond shape happening
there with
through that constellation and then here
on the other side you've got them um
you can see the more circular stuff and
that's kind of um
that's a seven sisters story the
pleiades constellation
um so you kind of see this coming
through and i don't know i've noticed
this in the
practice of carving this is that orion
one
it's hard to see but yeah so if you're
doing a boomerang
uh so it's basically two things with a
lot of the weapons
um so doing the boomerang both these so
this this is a
law stick here and so that's obviously a
round
one you know a rounded object
there um and so these both start out as
logs you know they're just a log
and so for that for this one
you know you basically start out
you know chopping it there until you get
that rounded or pointed
and but you see how i'm turning it
you're just always turning it like that
and then you've got it here and hold
them like baby's head
and it's funny it's like i don't know
i'm never allowed to do this
it's it's hard because if i try and do
it at work there's all this oh
shit going um workplace health and
safety things that are missing
messing up my my practice um
and someone inevitably calls security or
whatever
um and it's hard in the city because
people call the cops when you're
sitting somewhere with an axe like
but anyway i've done them all and i've
managed not to um
to die or be incarcerated for too long
or anything yet so that's that's pretty
good
um anyway yeah so you're holding it like
a little baby's head here
and you actually can't cut your fingers
off doing that and so you just keep
turning it and you're chopping chipping
away
and you're turning turning and you do it
all the way down like that you know
and it's that circular motion uh as
you're doing it
you've got this sort of haptic cognition
this embodiment
going in i don't know is it probably a
lot of you probably know about the new
materialism
that would be a way into thinking about
this kind of distributed cognition
where you have neural processes
happening beyond your skull
and actually into the tools and objects
that you use but then into the
relationships with people places
and entities all around you you're kind
of doing that
and you're working in these stories and
these places
as you cut you're cutting it into there
and so you're ending up this is like
a um a usb like a memory stick you know
you're encoding all the information into
that
and then you might etch some designs in
there that are like
little mnemonic triggers for some of
that information
now i've done here so that's a map of a
place there
that i've put in there but this one's
problematic because it's um
so it's uh it's it's it's black wattle
uh from a place where wattle is male
uh but i brought it down here and i've
carved it
on country where wattle is female
and so there's knowledge from elsewhere
and then there's knowledge from here in
there so i've got this really
problematic law stick
um that auntie had to flog me for
but not with yet um yeah
she's got her own sticks um so there's
that one there's that circle way
with the carving but then this one here
is um
this is cool i haven't shared this with
anyone yet these these things
um this one and i can't share too much
because it's very much
it's male activity and and you know it
can make
a woman sick like seeing me do this
um yeah
um not just a woman like um
any uh menstruating organism
um can get sick from watching me uh if i
was actually carving
i could could do this i could get sick
um anyway so i like uh
this one it's it's a log and you'll cut
it
like that first on that angle so you're
making a point all the way
along there and then you do it on the
other side
so what you end up with in the cross
section is kind of a
a diamond shape
carved out of the log and then you cut
off
those part both sides of the diamond and
it's still thick then
so you do it again you basically keep
making a diamond shape
and then you cut the ridges off that
sort of landscape of the wood
uh you bring it flatter until it comes
flat like this
you know so this one is um it's it's a
very different way of cutting
so you you're encoding a really
different kind of knowledge and a
different sort of way of thinking
you know into that wood um you know and
all the different carvings have
different ways
so a lot of the things i might make out
of bark like a shield or a coulomb or
something like that
and then a wooden shield that's a
different way of cutting as well
so it's different kinds of thinking that
are going into there
but then different stories of place from
where the wood comes from
um yeah and where you've been
walking and working and where those and
what stories come in there
so like each one is a chapter in the
book
so this one is um is really trying to
look at
um the probably problematic idea of uh
holistic
which is one of those words that's
overused and
under under um known
you know little understood you know um
so this was that chapter lemonade for
headaches
uh where i look at medicine a bit you
know and i'm trying to
look at um you know how it can be useful
um like a useful intersection between
indigenous knowledge and western science
is to um try and help uh
like mainstream researchers
include the variables of time and place
in their work so there's a lot of
studies where the
the results have have not been
replicable because
the researchers ignored time and place
especially
medicine research with with plants they
ignore where the plants is harvested
and they ignore the season in which
those plants are harvested
so they have variable results and so
they have inconclusive data
and so that's why you know um
there is no evidence that fish oil is
beneficial
to your health because they've not been
able to
have have replicable results in the
studies because they don't pay attention
to where they're catching the fish
or what time of year those fish are
harvested
so you might have one study that shows
like this miraculous bloody
effect on the kidneys and then the next
one will show no effect at all
yeah so um you know i try to help people
out with including those variables of
time and place
in their research and and that's a
valuable thing that can come from
aboriginal
knowledge it's part of the whole idea of
that the truth being in the aggregate of
all the stories
uh coming amongst each other you know um
you know every model and scientists know
this every model is wrong
but useful in some context
every model every theory is useful in
its
in in the right context but
it is wrong there isn't a unified theory
and some people are looking for that
like a holy grail because that's kind of
the project of westernism
is to find one unified narrative
one unified body of knowledge one
unified belief system one unified
language to rule them all
um is the project of westernism and it
doesn't exist
because you know it's a pluralistic
universe it's a pluralistic reality
that's just the physics
of the reality that we're living in
you know it's magical thinking to think
there's a unified field theory or
something like that
um and it's a damaging process to um
i don't know the entire society and
economic system and and
geopolitics and and everything is built
around that fantasy of
of of that one unified good
way and that somehow the anglo sphere is
going to be the repository
of all knowledge and uh you know that
will be
just unified into one monoculture
um which is kind of that's what the
apocalypse looks like
so the english word for universe you
know it's based on vertebrae
which means to become so verse is like
verso like turned into
and then uni is one so even the english
word for the universe is this fantasy of
turning everything into one monoculture
one unified system and a unified system
is
like what everything looked like before
the big bang
so nothing there is no
one one doesn't exist
you know one is just zero there's no
such thing as
one because it's not possible to have
anything existing in isolation
without being in relation to something
else
and then out to many other something
else's
you know it's we only exist in relation
to other things
and in different contexts the the
meaning of that
of that relation and that reality
changes
um yeah i'm offline on a bit
benjamin has a question about crash
subject
yeah yeah hey uh thanks for being here
and it's not quite a change of subject
it's
related to your your tool making i had a
question about
uh how you learned and specifically
um you know how old were you what's the
process and then
looking forward do you think that the
craft that you learned
is being passed on in a sustainable way
um yeah it is
but um a lot of people think it's
it's dead and gone a lot of our own
people think that too that that's a
discontinuity
but it's happening in the same spaces
where
people are sneaking in at night first
peoples are sneak
sneaking in at night to that place tyson
mentioned and um stealing their own
ochre
um it's happening like that um i i'm
finding that the culture is
is being held like quietly and privately
by people of knowledge uh all over the
place
they just don't talk to anthropologists
and they don't talk to
the media and um you know while they
have things that they want to share with
the world
um like old man juma in my book you know
he has things that he wants to share
with the world to sort of make a ritual
um
action in spirit occur you know
uh to you know he he wants to enact that
and so he's given me those things to
pass on to the world
you know these are just um
you know they're not though they're not
they're not those things
they're not those deeper knowledges and
and understandings
you know um yeah these are the sort of
way of bringing people into that and
gradually bringing people back into
relation
um you know which kind of needs to occur
hey i saw a question pop up about gender
there
yes that was hannah this is a i mean
it's a really highly problematic thing
it's a big contested issue um in our
communities
as well and it's a very hard thing to to
talk about
um if you're worried about um
maintaining a brand or anything um
or maintaining i don't know the ability
to have a live livelihood or anything
like that
because there's pretty much not anything
that anyone can say that
a bunch of people aren't going to be
upset about at the moment there
at the same as everywhere else uh
fortunately i'm not really concerned
with my brand so
i can talk up as much as i like about
that
um unfortunately i don't have a fixed
opinion about it because every
unfortunately i like because i am
a fluid and adaptive sort of node in a
complex adaptive system
you know i'm constantly being
transformed by
uh new information encounters that come
in so i guess my
thinking around that changes every few
days
so it'll never be the same it's not the
same as what i even wrote in that book
today but it'll probably be something
completely different tomorrow
but i tell you someone good to read from
the states if you're over there
from america anyway turtle island um kim
tallbear
kim tallbear has done a really a lot of
really interesting work on
decolonizing sexuality um and she
she challenges uh both heteronormative
and homo normative
um uh ideologies around sexuality
um and you know she even challenges that
uh
kind of trendy idea of of two-spirit
two-spirit people that's come out of the
united states
um and she kind of
she has a lot of really good knowledge
about what sexuality
was prior to uh european colonization
um that's really interesting
uh she talks about it in terms of um
making
kin and that that's the purpose
of of of sex and sexuality
you know um it's kind of like um
you know in the old days if you were an
ambassador it was really different
um to what diplomats do today there was
quite a bit of sex involved because you
had to establish those relations first
you know and a lot of it wasn't
constrained by the same kind of labels
um as it is today
i and i think a lot of settlers and
particularly missionaries and
and stuff like that were really um like
horrified by what they saw
and and a lot of that so most of it was
not recorded
actually you know almost there's only a
few hints here and there of what was
uh in terms of sexuality and sex and uh
gender and gender roles and all that
kind of thing and there's a lot of
misapprehensions
so everybody's taken on board the
mythology of uh
you know men were the hunters and women
where the gatherers
that's kind of a universally
unchallenged assumption
uh that a lot of science and psychology
and
um ah governance everything
you know is based on that idea and it's
kind of bullshit
um and i think if you really look into
it
you'll see you know like i mentioned
that um
that neanderthal men and women had the
same fracture patterns
uh in their skeleton skeletal remains
um which is really a really important
thing
they just noted that you know in the
studies but they didn't like
draw any conclusions from that because i
i think it would unravel
pretty much all of you know uh
civilization and society as we know it
to acknowledge that women were bloody
hunting
women in europe were hunting megafauna
bros they were doing it the same way as
the men were
you know um yeah
i like you know they can acknowledge
that neanderthals are a bit more
advanced
than we thought you know because like
especially after they found out that
most europeans have neanderthal dna
um then they discovered that ah actually
they had a really advanced
chaotic culture oh yeah in the end it
wasn't cro-magnon
cro-magnon had a 10 bigger brain than
modern humans that's huge
um so they're able to acknowledge all
that uh but
they couldn't they couldn't revise the
gender role thing
you know that that's that's like you
know the entire
like civilization is built on you know
the subjugation
you know just by accident of birth
of half the population that's how
civilizations work
there there isn't there isn't a
matriarchal civilization
that that's never existed you know
matriarchies are what
happens outside of a civilized
controlled
if civilization is patriarchal
it's necessarily patriarchal because you
have to separate from the mother
in order to become this domesticated
insane
beast who can keep eating itself
you know you have to separate from the
mother deny the mother hate the mother
be hostile to the mother
and this these cities that we live in
now they're all hostile to mothers
particularly and certainly to women
you know and i don't care what anyone
says it's a terrible place to be a woman
i i've i've you know
i've i've i often ask men you know
would you be a woman like
you know like especially when men are
telling me that everything's just equal
and they don't know what
what women are whinging about i said
well would you would you be a woman
come on seriously i can straight up
right now would you be a woman
and they always say no and i'm like
right so you know what's going on
you know you wouldn't want to subject
yourself to that
you know there's a um ah
it's just horrific most of the women i
know like live in fear i mean they have
really good mechanisms for dealing with
it
and most are pretty kind of happy and
i don't know where they get that
strength from to be that
you know but but it's in fear and they
don't have the same
man i used to have this um
this man used to follow me home from
work like
i'd knock off work and i'd go home and
every day he'd be following me in his
car and like vigorously masturbating
while he looked at me
um like so he'd park you know 100 meters
off and he'd watch me walking
and like the whole car would be shaking
and that happened every day
it was just a normal part of my day i
never once felt unsafe
one day he didn't show up and all that
god where's that where's that fellow god
then the next day he shows up and he's
there again
and the car's just sort of full only
rocking
so i walked up to the car and i said i
missed you yesterday bros like
are you okay what's happening he goes oh
my dad died and
you know upset i'm like oh can i do
anything for you buzz
that's that's terrible you know can i
help you he said oh can you wear the
white t-shirt tomorrow
i'm like yeah bros i can do that for you
um
you know it's just not a threat but if i
was a female
like there's a really good chance like
at least one in ten that that guy's
gonna try and kill me
you know but i i don't have to have any
fear of that and not because i'm big and
strong it's just
you know anyway i don't know
it's um it's just a really crappy setup
and that's that's the civilized relation
between men and women
um and i don't like it
and nobody particularly likes it so
i just i don't want to participate in
that
how about you anybody else want to
participate in that anymore
all the women i know feel incredibly
grateful to have been born a woman in
this lifetime
someone's just said yeah anna did you
have any
follow-up question
yeah i was particularly curious on to
how
these feminine and masculine concepts
map
onto the items that you showed us
and i think you mentioned a die as well
that's viewed differently in two
different cultures so
i was wondering if you could speak to
that but if you feel it has been
covered enough then that's okay too um
yeah um and and i mean i'm just um
you know i'm creating these things
within the tradition
the traditions that i belong to um
you know and within the the ideas that
you know the knowledge has been passed
to me along that
and um i i guess it's it's dealing with
uh
female and male energies and of course
everybody's got um
a bit of both in different uh
sort of percentages in their being and
and that's fluid because that can change
throughout your life
you know and it does change throughout
everybody's life
because if you if you make it through to
extreme old age
uh to to elderhood you know um
the women grow beards in old age and
the men grow tits it's there is a um
you know and and there's you know all
your hormone levels change
when you get older so throughout your
life there is a shift
in that that masculine and feminine
energy so that's why elders are able to
do
uh different things and they have their
own kind of secret business that they do
together
um they don't particularly share with
everybody else
uh because they're working with a very
different um
sort of admixture of men's business and
women's business
um as they go along to those really high
levels of knowledge
um you know but the rest of us will be
sitting from moment to moment in
you know with male energy in our belly
or female energy in our belly
and you know there's only certain ways
that those things can come alongside
each other productively or safely
uh so there's lots of community ritual
activity and um
you know man or woman together you know
things that we do
and all of the the um
ritual and knowledge and practice around
children and child rearing
these are all points of intersection
where those
energies can come together but um
but there's a lot of things that they
have to be separate because
a man's energy is uh what's just often
described too in aboriginal cultures as
sour
like it's a bitter and sour energy
and that that kind of like a lot of
people hearing that from the first time
goes
hmm yeah that's true you know it's a
different
smell it's a different chemistry you
know to the spirit of that
and then um whereas women's women's
energy is
is it's a it's different it's um
it's it's sweet and it's um
it's unctuous and um and and it's it's
it's a different kind of energy
um and the problem with uh bringing
those together
um in in the wrong way and in the wrong
contexts
culturally is that that men's energy can
sour
a woman's energy and and a woman's
energy
can often like completely destroy a
male's energy as well
you know um so it's um it's important in
a lot it's important to maintain um
male and female spaces you know where
activities can be
done that aren't going to make people
sick um
yeah but at the same time
you know it's not every single person is
completely one thing or the other thing
you know there's a lot of there's a lot
of interesting stuff that happens in the
in between
and that's pretty much a foundational
concept of indigenous cultures
as that um everything good happens in in
between
in that invisible relational space and
some people
are born to just inhabit that space and
those are sacred people
you know um and special people like
they've got a special
purpose and they have their own business
um and their own like uh
you know ways of working that spirit
that that are absolutely essential to
the whole community
um uh a lot of this stuff has been lost
and there are a lot there's a lot of
people doing the good work of finding
their way back to that
and and recovering that law and like i
said on turtle island
kim told there is is is the best i've
seen for that
um really worth uh
you know listening to any of her
lectures that you can find or
reading any of her papers you you love
that stuff
we are two minutes beyond the hour tyson
do you have
time for any more questions or must we
let you go
um yeah i don't think hang on give me
let me
check my calendar but i don't i um i can
go over a bit
yeah don't don't be don't be rushing the
yarn
it's all i've allowed until midday for
this so
you can go a bit more good luck all
right well that would be wonderful there
are questions still
rolling in um nicholas i would love for
you to ask
um whichever of your questions is most
alive to you
now
can you guys hear me yeah yeah
it doesn't have to be a question either
like sometimes people just want to say
something and then they have to reframe
it as a question
like if you just want to say something
like just say it
yeah so so tyson um tysons
thank you for hosting hey
for being here giving such a an
interesting talk my disclaimer is that i
haven't read your book yet
it's arriving in two days um but this is
this you may you may have something to
say about this or maybe you've addressed
it in your book already
so um a return to an indigenous
worldview has come into vogue
as an alternative future to techno
utopian hyper capitalism
in most capitalist circles notably in
eisenstein's work
uh robin wall kimmerer andreas weber
and so on it's also been subverted and
consumerized
as a trope by capital in films and
series like avatar
altered garbage and wealthy retreats to
eco villages
in mark fisher's essay terminator versus
avatar
he argues that while we may wish to
disavow capitalism
by embracing our true primitive selves
his words
uh victimized by the military-industrial
complex he claims that there are no
primitive societies anymore
and triumphing and nostalgic return to
the past is a betrayal of our ability to
think
alternate futures to capitalist realism
thus
avatar the idea of a return to mother
earth is a nostalgic moral critique
of capitalism that is dead in the water
because its gaze is fixed on the past
and it has no techno-political teeth to
rival hegemonic neoliberalism's
terminator or moloch
in the present so those are contentious
headwinds and i'm wondering what your
thoughts are about this
ah so many thoughts look that you can't
return to primitivism you can't return
to a primitivism that has never existed
it's a myth primitive cultures have
never existed
they don't exist they've never existed
so the idea of returning to them is
insane
you know that human cultures have been
complex adaptive
we've been making meaning for a million
years symbolic reasoning
and you might say what i thought it was
just ten thousand but
no this homo erectus was doing designs
symbolic designs abstract designs on
shelves
and they found those shells a million
years old so for at least a million
years i would say even more
you know our custodial species
has been making meaning you know through
symbolic reasoning
you know and this is very complex
cultures so if you're um
you know projecting onto the past like
that anthropologist with yanamani
indians saying well he
they even though they've reported their
genealogies to me they couldn't possibly
know their genealogies because they're
primitive
only my computer can know their
genealogies it's just insane
it's this um oh
you know it's like those um you know the
paleontologists
know the archaeologists for a long time
they were finding these um
these round discs like bone or
or stone or whatever i'm finding these
round discs with notches around the
outside
um and always around like you know 28
31 you know around that kind of number
and they were finding them all over the
place you know all around the world like
not just from one culture they were
finding those what the hell are these
i will never know what these are you
know for many decades until finally
there was a female archaeologist
who went i know what that is i could run
anywhere in my purse right now
this is like women tracking their cycle
to control their fertility what the fuck
i mean it's really simple you know i
mean
this idea of these primitive savage
bloody animal people walking around
monkeys
you know with clubs is just insane and
the idea of a return to that
is insane um and people's there's a
there's a really
important phenomenon to acknowledge
which is white activism
and it's it's this idea of um
you know um sort of white people
you know settlers basically uh modern
civilized people domesticated people um
trying to reclaim some kind of
indigeneity
in the past and bring it forward to the
present uh in a way where they'll be
able to keep all of their shit
like they want to be able to it's like
yeah i
i want to become
i want to become that neo-primitive
person
so that i can regain some authenticity
and you know a basic way of living in
the world that is human
um but i want to keep all my stolen
resources
it's like stolen land i want to keep i
want to keep this land as capital
and all of the you know blood soaked
resources and bank accounts and
and and quad bikes and three houses and
everything i want to be able to keep all
that
but be this indigen indigenous being
um so yeah that there's that white
activism going on
and it the i guess there's another
danger with that which is to generalize
that out to everybody who's
who's genuinely seeking to find the
fragments of their humanity
and build from the pattern that they
find there to reclaim
you know a way of being human uh that is
not infected by this
algorithm of destruction which is not
in our dna we're not
some white fantasy of yanamani indians
just
struggling and fighting each other in
endless horrific
violence until we all die and destroy
the planet
there's this idea that oh human beings
are naturally just
just horrific things that wreck the
world around us
that's bullshit and people who are
looking to try and recover
some way of being human um that is
real and that actually occupies our
ecological niche
and our our role as a custodial species
on the planet
that's a different thing and i don't
like it when people try and lump
those genuine seekers in with white
activists
um you know who are really just trying
to make a cultural
arc where they can keep all of their
stolen goods
and and carry it across into the next
world
yeah that uh
the white atavism that you described
there sounds like a
a match made in hell between russo's
state of nature
and and the maga like make america great
again play
yeah it's like a mishmash of both uh
and and trying to keep trying to keep
the moral purity of one
and the the stolen wealth of the other
yeah
yeah so so hey nicholas
are you are you jewish or israeli or
something like that
i'm uh i'm half jewish half catholic so
yeah yeah
so i was looking at well which half was
anyway um
i was just thinking about that like the
the cultural
and economic success of the jewish
diaspora everywhere
i mean you know um and israel aside
because that's a different beast
um completely but in the diaspora all
everywhere around
around the world um just absolutely
amazing
so this is a community it has no
government funding
it has no you know it
basically it's a community that's
looking after itself
it's a community that has its own
internal economy um you know the kids
finish school
in the daytime you know in the host
country and then they go to
you know hebrew school at night and that
hebrew school's not paid for by the
government that's
its own community is throwing in and
you know um so basically you've got a
community that's that's held itself
together
and maintained an ancient tradition
with absolutely no problem at the same
time as mastering
you know the cultures and languages of
whatever host country they're in
you know and maintaining these these
amazing communities
um just everywhere with with huge
amounts of cultural success
you know um so i don't know this idea
that there are no
cultures left in the world you know
there are no cultural traditions left i
mean that you can see the continuity
there
of jewish culture everywhere you go in
the world
um you know and you can see the same
kinds of continuities everywhere else
a lot of us as indigenous people i think
could learn a lot from the jews
in terms of um you know stabilizing and
being able to
self-support and separate our culture
from the mainstream but just
you know keep it there but then also be
able to
you know distribute our gifts to the the
culture as well
so you know i mean where would we be
without seinfeld
um so you've got this culture producing
all these amazing things that everybody
wants
and um and that's the relation you know
that we have
and i guess you know um and
there's no particular plan for it um
i think people like to project plans
like the protocols of the elders of zion
and assume that there has to be a plant
um but i i don't see that in jewish
culture i see this um
you know it's just that idea of
fostering the conditions for emergence
you know people are behaving and living
in the right way
and good things come out of that and i
and i guess that that's a human way to
be
um if there's a if there's a plan for a
kind of universal jewish cabal
to manipulate global economies i'm not
in on it
yeah but that's just it i just think i
think i think the jewish culture is a
perfect example of
you know of not having a plan you know
but having an an an ethical pattern that
has followed and then
you know the good things emerge from
that
you know um yeah it's just a
a collective sort of supportive
you know uh a group of all very
different individuals all together
just um allowing
you know creativity to emerge um
allowing things to emerge and now
allowing you know governance patterns
and things like that to happen i mean
that's what i see in the diaspora
that's not what i see in israel that's a
different thing like i said but that's
what i see in the diaspora
and i think that like the jewish
diaspora is a pretty damn good model of
um
of how to be in in really and how to
deal with uncertainty
and not just survive it but thrive and
be as happy as hell
so i don't know any miserable jews like
every jew i've ever met been like
really smart and really happy and um
yeah even when they're fasting
i wasn't happy like when i fasted with
my jewish mates like i did
that big long one you know and and i was
miserable as shit but they were all
really happy man
thanks for your answer tyson i have a
lot but i don't want to monopolize here
so
back to you tyson flows
thank you there's uh there's a few
questions in here getting
lots of upvotes but i'm just going to go
to the most recent one right now
and that is darren's question and then
after that would love to go to
christian and thomas if we have time so
darren
oh hey hi tyson um so someone can you
hear me
yeah yeah okay great yeah so some of us
were just on a call
a couple hours ago we were talking about
you know
greek dialogue and sort of some ideas
that they had about
you know how to relate to each other so
that you could have a good conversation
you know a conversation that sort of is
fruitful
or leads to us being able to do things
together that we couldn't do separately
you know in your book you talk a lot
about you know yarny about how you get
together
with people and you want to have this
it's it's kind of like
conversation it's kind of like
storytelling it's kind of like
experimental storytelling where you
figure out what's true
and so i was just curious you know like
when you hear about the greeks do you
just think oh hey
they were just getting those greek dudes
they were just yarny
or different or how would you compare
the two what do we
not get about it well i think the only
difference is um
is abstraction so in the the greek stoa
a lot of
what was discussed was was abstracted
and um and sort of um not
not sitting within a context a living
context
um so it's that birth of reductionism
you know that idea of okay so for
example being able to separate the
concepts
so inventing a word for nature and
separating that
from the word for society which so
in indigenous cultures and in most human
cultures prior to that
the invention of the stower um
prior to those greek yarns you know
there was no separate concept for nature
or environment
you know uh so that was i'd say that's
the only difference
but for the rest of it in in the the
form and shape of it i think there's a
lot of similarities
you know particularly just the flow of
it
and that kind of respect and the idea
the idea that the truth could be found
in the aggregate
and that there wasn't this idea of uh
with a lot of the traditions anyway
um because there were different
different schools of thought of course
over time and even
at the same time um this idea that
you know you weren't there to um
to dominate through discussion and to
have your story come out on top
and for yours to become the dominant
narrative
you know they weren't seeking a dominant
narrative they were seeking
not even a consensus but they were kind
of
seeking a pluralistic aggregate of truth
where you know the outliers on the bell
curve
are interesting and
that story you know adds to the context
of the rest of the bell
you know what i mean um but rather than
just focusing exclusively on the
majority opinion
or even more dangerously just focusing
on the outlier
stories which is always dangerous um
yeah that they were able to try and try
and form this
this this holistic view of all the
stories together
and to find sort of a shape of the truth
within that
you know you do that but but we don't
say that because there's there's no word
for truth
you know there aren't these abstracts so
we've never had to separate
out all these ideas and talk about them
because they just
are that's part of the contextual
foundation of the whole yarn in the
first place
so you're coming to the yarn and ninety
percent of it is just context that
doesn't even need to be said
so you can have a quite an economy of
words you know
and you don't have to listen like this
here there's where i'm talking for like
maybe eight or ten minutes at a time
straight that doesn't have to happen
it's a lot of back and forth you know
and unless like there's an old person
telling us
long story or something then you don't
have that
but then then old people only tell the
old story like the entire story
you know in a really specific genre
that's you know telling a story to
children
because most of the time you only get a
fragment of the story that's relevant to
a place
or a context or you know you'll only
hear part of the story
and it'll be so you receive that story
out of order
over a number of years in different
contexts rather than being told from
start to finish
in that way so i guess everything's kind
of different
i don't know and that uh you know we
impose these time structures but also
spatial
structures i mean now a lot of people
think if you're sitting in a circle
you're doing it but you're not you're
just turning a straight line into a
circle
you start with one person then everybody
gets their turn with the talking stick
as it goes around
and everybody in order just monologues
while everybody has to listen to them
um that's not yawning either
yeah it's hard to describe even what
johnny means
christian would you like to ask your
question
christian did you hear me
let's go to thomas yeah i'm here sorry
about that christian's here
okay
um what was my question
i had to write it a few times so i
should probably refer back to it rather
than try to do it from memory
uh okay
is mythology something to be held in a
purely
allegorical way something to extract
meaning from the analysis
and then integrate it into one's
worldview
and your sense making and then kind of
like
put in its place or discarded or
is there something to be gained from an
emotional commitment
to a mythological story um
something like divine and sacred that
you can like
it should it can be alive in you um
or yeah it's a question of like how to
balance yeah like a
relating to the divine through mythology
uh while allowing for like
pluralism at the level of you know
understanding what's going on so to
speak
well mythology doesn't exist
um and the divine doesn't exist
at least as a separate thing from
everything else
you know what what people are calling
mythology now
or myths all these sorts of things well
all they are
is a it's just a model
it's a model of reality that's useful in
some contexts
so that's when you fucking use it you
know
like it's like any other you know as
newton you do use newton's
physics like you i mean you do every day
in a lot of the technology that you use
and it's a useful model of reality in
some
circumstances but for the zoom meeting
to work
and for the the relative time to happen
is this signals buzzing up to a
satellite and then bouncing down into a
million places around the globe at once
um newton that wouldn't work we wouldn't
have this zoom
on the newton model we've got to go to
einstein for a bit
you know which is also only useful in
some contexts it's useful to make the
zoom meeting where
to make the tech work so that's that's
the model for that
uh what people are calling myths and
mythology uh
deeply layered things you know and
mostly people are only coming in at the
folklore
children's fable level of the mythology
and that has a purpose it's mostly just
to put kids to sleep
god damn it at night because we need a
minute to ourselves fuck
um but you know the rest of the deep
layers of mythology
um you know they contain
maps memory knowledge that are useful
in contexts they're useful
in you know there's parts of myths that
are just for women
or just for old women and that they only
apply
you know as a model in a situation
you know such as inducting a young woman
into this area
of reality or something like that and
that's what it's for
um you know but it's also for medicine
it's also for this and that
this whole universes of knowledge in
there in every
mythology there's there's various models
that are applicable in different
contexts
but useless in other contexts so why
would you even look at it
um but it's the same as everything else
you know there are i mean i guess you
could think of a lot of engagement with
myth and ritual as uh
in terms of uh simulation you know
uh simulation and modeling that you do
to try and predict how a system will
behave and all that sort of stuff
it's the same thing it's just like a
it's just like software
but it's um you know software for
the mind not just your mind but you know
the mind of the sentient uh landscapes
and context that you inhabit
um you know your mythology is just a
handy bit of software for that
it's no big deal it's just the same as
everything else
it's a handy model of theory that you
can apply to certain
concepts as soon as you elevate it to
this this this
goddamn spiritual uh thing of
of this you you've got to have this
religious or or something
or that that's that's that's the place
this is the stuff where um
i take my moment to talk like this you
know this
is my yeah it's like nah that's not what
it is
uh yeah you just uh
it's just a tool like anything else just
engage with it
and you don't put it up there but you
don't put it down there either as
something to denigrate
it's no more or less rigorous than any
other body of knowledge or any other
intellectual tool
has its uses some people misuse it and
you know become fucking gurus and stuff
like this and just wreck everything
some people establish ideologies based
out of these mythologies and
[Music]
wreck everything but that's coming back
to that trap of going
i have the solution i have i have the
secret knowledge that you need
i've got it you know everybody should
think like this
and then you get like i don't know a
group of like the mean girls from high
school clustering around you and
following you and
and spreading that and bloody backing
you up and
teasing anybody who doesn't or mobbing
anybody who doesn't like
parrot your idea um it's just insane
like ah i'm just so sick of ideologies
and bloody belief systems and
it's people's bloody solutions and
tinkered
little structures that they think you
know can
somehow stand a test of time or have
any application in this world
just like just calm down it's just a
model
use it when it's useful
sorry man that was a long way to say
that and i know time's running out
that was really good um theater i would
love for you to finish us off with your
um question
uh well yeah i can't resist the urge
to look for secret knowledge
but in your book uh you mentioned how
rhyme and alliteration were great ways
of disseminating knowledge
and one one thing that stood out to me
in the back of the book in your last
chapter and you also talked about it
with omajuma
is the seven spirit families so
this is something i found through a rap
song
actually uh it's from christoph crane
he created a double album called kairos
and he goes quite in depth about the
seven
spirit families and the seven
constellations
and i was just wondering if you could
expand on that more because i've
kind of been consumed by it
it is um it's just a rabbit hole it's a
fractal rabbit hole that one
was and you just um it's
yeah you start to get a sense that that
we all
i mean i've heard that explained as just
you know um just a universal pattern
recognition thing that
that humans or many name way of the same
sort of shapes and so if there's a vague
man shape of something in the sky then
everyone will see that as a man
but that's i mean
that's bullshit again like you look you
look at orion
it's just basically a square
in the sky that everybody goes yeah
that's a that's a dude
but not just any dude that that's a
warrior or a hunter like for
everybody on the planet so you know
like you know that there's a common
origin
uh story body of knowledge you know
you know that there's or at least a hell
of a big embassy
going around and a lot more exchange and
a lot more
ocean travel like we like
we know that that homo erectus had sea
going vessels
homo erectus that's a long time ago
you know and i mean they're trying out
they're holding on to the out of africa
theory
that's why like every time there's a
there's a discovery
we get every year there's an
announcement like oh um
yeah these this archaeological evidence
suggests that uh
aboriginal people have actually been
here for more than 100 000 years
you know but the record still says
60 000 or 60 000 plus they can't move it
on from that because the math doesn't
work for the out of africa theory
chances are like from from everything
that i keep looking at
i've seen there's a really there's a
really good argument for um
for people coming out of uh here
australia like our old people's stories
say
um or you know what was i mean at a time
when australia wasn't even just
australia it was just
you know part of a big asian sort of
land mass um
yeah chances are people actually came
out from there
um like modern humans um
but then even this idea of modern humans
is a bit of a misnomer because
you know modern humans is just a hybrid
of seven different bloods
and i guess you can look at those
studies you know you've got your
homoflorences homo neandophthalus
uh you know your cro-magnon and your
homo erectus and all right
and then the denisovans and then
something else it's like seven bloods
and you know
the idea of all those families coming
together again is
kind of nice you know um and yeah old
man
that's that that's basically the purpose
of the book is it's just a delivery
system
um for you know this this spiritual
vaccine
of his six symbols that have just uh he
wanted it to go out into the world
and so this is just a delivery system
that's just a bit of
marketing and packaging around that in a
book people keep reading the book and
saying it's changing change them at the
genetic level which is so weird because
that's what he said would happen
he said this changed people's dna see
got to change the dna
bring them seven spirit family and it's
so weird
you know like jim rat said it changed
his dna
how random is that so different people
from all walks of life
i got women calling me up saying like
my husband doesn't recognize my smell
anymore my smell changed after i read
your book
you know i've changed it to molecular
and chemical level
um i keep getting that feedback and and
us and
nobody can pinpoint which words are in
the book that did that
and they keep looking for it in the
words don't even look at the words
if there's just like there's six images
in there from an
old black wizard in australia
who's like just basically um used me to
cast a spell on the world to change
everybody's dna
and bring everyone together
so i think we're all going to be
recognizing those
stars and those stories and and find our
way back to that
or we're just all going to die so you
know but only one of those two things
um whichever way we gotta have a good
laugh while we're doing it
i reckon well thank you encouraging for
encouraging the good laughs here in this
space tyson
and being generous with your time and i
really appreciate you
uh just being here and sharing this the
space and time with us
thank you everybody i gotta answer that
question somebody said is is old man
embodied like yeah he's a real dude i
think um
you know he's got a body and like a
camper thing and everything but i've
never seen him sleep um
but i was talking to him on the phone
like yesterday so he definitely exists
in this reality but probably a few
different ones
he's one of them quantum people anyway
there's a there's a photo there's photos
of me oh wow
uh do you want me to show your photo
just before we leave yeah that would be
awesome you can drag it right there
yeah somewhere in
these for the launch
there was pictures where is it um
ah man i'm sorry this technique here it
is that's all right i got it
now i've just got to do this sherry
screeny thing and
i'll make you host um i hope it's not
that guy that
follows you in the car though secretly
man anyone's welcome to follow me in the
car thank you
it's fine um
you got uh post access
oh cool thanks man i'm just going to do
a share screen
and i'll just leave you with a picture
so he does exist
there's my little daughter onyx
that's me there's old man there
yeah cheeky lovely and terrifying
i'm a human being
all right thank you tyson
no worries i'll see you later
all right and tomorrow everybody and at
the stoa
is a wee space communitas type practice